GLORY
DAYS!
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
天下統一の道を行く王 嬴政(えいせい)のもと
By the decision of Ying Zheng, the king that wished to unite all of China,
the State of Qin began its invasion of the State of Wei.
秦国(しんこく)は 魏国(ぎこく)へと侵攻した
The enemy blocking their way is the legendary Great General, Lian Po.
立ちはだかる敵は
伝説の大将軍 廉頗(れんぱ)
若き将たちは 大いなる武功を狙い
この苛烈な戦場に挑む
Young generals take on this relentless battlefield in hopes of rendering great military achievements.
（王翦(おうせん)）
よろしい　私の兵をそなたに預ける
Very well. I shall bequeath my soldiers to you.
And if we join that with the units nearby, it will be 5,000.
更に 周辺にいる部隊を束ねれば
5,000になろう
それらを率いる権限を
そなたに授ける
I grant you the rights to lead them.
壁(へき)！
Bi!
（王翦）そなたは
これより 5,000の将として…
You will now be acting as a general of 5,000
and attack the Jiang Yan and the State of Wei Army!
魏国軍 姜燕(きょうえん)を迎撃せよ
私が 5,000の将…
Me? A 5,000-Man General?!
（壁）勝てる… 勝てるぞ！
姜燕 何するものぞ！
I can win... I can win this!
There's nothing Jiang Yan can do!
The enclosed land. A depression surrounded by sheer cliffs.
“囲地”… 文字どおり
切り立った壁に囲まれた窪地(くぼち)だ
If one enters by the somewhat gentle slope on one side,
一方の側にある やや傾斜の緩い
斜面を入り口とすれば―
their exit on the opposite side will be the narrow path surrounded by cliffs.
反対側にある崖に挟まれた細い道が
出口となる
攻める側が崖の上に布陣できれば
If a force can be encamped on top of those cliffs,
高い所から矢を射(う)ち込み
敵の兵力をそいだうえで―
on top of reducing the enemy's manpower by firing arrows from a high ground,
once a chance to grab victory seems likely, that force can descend the mountains and take down the enemy.
勝機を見計らって 崖を駆け下り
敵を討つことができる
（魏兵）止まるな！
敵の矢をまともに受けるぞ！
Don't slow down!
We're taking the enemy's arrows head-on!
Hurry and run out of here!
急いで駆け抜けろ！
（魏兵）
ムリだ！ 前が詰まって 進めない！
We can't! It's so crowded up ahead we can't move!
（壁）攻撃を受けた側は
周囲の崖に逃げ道を阻まれ
The ones being hit by attacks will have their path of escape blocked by the cliffs surrounding them.
唯一の出口である細い道に
殺到すれば―
If they flood their one, narrow exit,
渋滞して 動きが取れなくなる
they'll get congested and won't be able to move.
（魏兵）
ダメだ！ 後ろも敵に塞がれた！
Dammit! Enemies are blocking us from behind as well!
With the enemy's focus on the exit,
（壁）敵の意識が出口に集中すれば
後ろに回り込むことも たやすい
it will be an easy task to attack them from behind.
In other words, if the enemy can be lured into that enclosed area and you can secure the tops of the cliffs,
つまり 囲地に敵を誘い込み
崖の上を押さえることができれば
you can easily defeat even twice one's numbers!
倍の数の敵でも 容易に討てるのだ
（部下）壁さま　至る所で
我が軍が 敵を圧倒しておりますぞ
Lord Bi! Our army is overwhelming the enemy throughout!
もはや 敵は逃げることも
反撃することもできますまい
It is doubtful that the enemy can run or counterattack at this point!
よし…
Okay... Okay... we can beat them!
よし！
討てるぞ！
5,000 men led by me...
5,000の兵を率いた この私が―
１万の兵を率いた
廉頗四天王のひとり―
will defeat 10,000 men led by one of Lian Po's Four Heavenly Kings, Jiang Yan!
将軍 姜燕を討てるのだ！
Do not give the enemy an opportunity to rally!
敵に態勢を立て直す隙を与えず
一気に勝負をつける！
End this with one attack!
All units, descend the mountains and take down the enemy general, Jiang Yan!
全軍 崖を駆け下り
敵の将軍 姜燕を討ち取れ！
Was this really the best decision, Lord Wang Jian?
（部下）本当に
よろしかったのですか？ 王翦さま
Entrusting 5,000 men to that Thousand-Man General, Bi?
壁とかいう あの千人将に
5,000もの兵を任せて
私の目に狂いはない
There is nothing wrong with my judgment.
He will make for a good decoy.
（王翦）あやつは いい囮(おとり)になる
Double Bluff
Lord Jiang Yan! The enemy is descending the cliffs in droves!
（部下）姜燕さま
敵が続々と崖を下りてきます
どうやら 全軍で
この本陣を狙ってくるようです
It seems they're using all of their units to target our headquarters!
Do not let the defense formations collapse.
（姜燕）守備の陣形を崩すな
十分に引き付けて 迎え撃て
Draw their attention and engage them.
Yes, sir!
Lord Jiang Yan!
（部下）姜燕さま！
There is an enemy that broke through the defensive unit and is heading towards us!
（部下）守備陣を突破し
こちらに迫ってくる敵がいます
With our progress halted like this,
（部下）こうなったら
打って出て たたきつぶしてやるか
maybe we should sortie and crush them?
（部下）それとも
ここで待ち受けて返り討ちにするか
Or perhaps we should wait for them to come and defeat them when they try to attack?
What do you say, Lord Jiang Yan?
（部下）
いかがいたしましょう 姜燕さま
Lord Jiang Yan?
姜燕さま？
Lord Jiang Yan!
（部下）姜燕さま？
（部下）臆するな！ 進め！
一気に姜燕の首を取るのだ！
Do not hesitate! Forward!
Head straight for Jiang Yan's head!
（部下）壁さま！
Lord Bi!
Reporting from the unit in the forest to the Northeast!
（部下）北東の森に
展開していた部隊から報告です！
（部下）ほかの戦場の話など
今は どうでもよい！
We're not concerned about the affairs of other battlefields right now!
But...
しかし その部隊が
昨日まで戦っていた相手が―
The enemy that unit was fighting up until yesterday suddenly disappeared,
突然 姿を消してしまったので
念のため報告をと
so we thought it best to give a report...
敵の部隊が姿を消した？
The enemy unit... disappeared?
まさか ひょっとして…
Could it be that he...?
（兵士）な… なに？
What?!
Enemies! The Wei guys are up on the cliffs!
（部下）
敵だ！ 魏のヤツらが崖の上に！
That's impossible! Where in the world did they come from?!
（部下）
そんなバカな！ 一体 どこから…
弓矢で合図を送って―
He sent a signal with his arrow to coordinate with units fighting in other areas?
ほかの場所で戦っている軍と
連携していたのか
いかん！
今すぐ 全軍を崖の上に戻らせろ！
No!
All units, return to atop the cliffs at once! The advantage of the enclosed land has been taken by the enemy!
囲地の利を敵に奪われるぞ！
We can't, Lord Bi!
（部下）ダメです 壁さま
間に合いません！
We won't make it in time!
（部下）
崖の上を敵に押さえられました！
We're being pushed back by the enemies on top of the cliffs!
（部下）壁さま！
（部下）今度は何だ？
Lord Bi!
What is it this time?!
（部下）後ろから敵が！
（部下）なに？
Enemies from the rear!
What?!
いかん！ 壁さまを守れ！
Oh no! Protect Lord Bi!
（部下）逃げろ！
（部下）しかし どこへ…
Run!
But where?!
Just run for now!
とにかく走れ！
味方を集めて 態勢を立て直し―
We'll gather allies, regroup, and find an opening to charge through no matter what it takes!
なんとしても
突破口を見いだすのだ！
そなたが
この戦を指揮している将だな？
So you are the general commanding this attack... correct?
This is... one of the Lian Po Four Heavenly Kings... Jiang Yan?!
これが 廉頗四天王のひとり 姜燕か
My body... won't move!
体が… 動かぬ
General... Wang Jian!
（壁）王翦将軍！
Wang
Jian
You are Jiang Yan, correct?
うぬが姜燕だな？
（王翦）崖の上は 全て制した
I have gained control over the top of all of the the cliffs.
囲地の利を 再び こちらが握った…
He regained... the advantage of the enclosed land... for our side.
（王翦）うぬの負けだ 姜燕
You have lost, Jiang Yan.
（部下）そんなバカな…
That's madness!
（部下）我々が
敵の援軍に気づかぬはずは…
How could we have not noticed the presence of enemy reinforcements?!
It's all over!
（魏兵）もうダメだ！
（魏兵）皆殺しにされるぞ！
We're going to be slaughtered!
Lord Bi... is this...
（部下）壁さま これは…
（部下）我々の勝ちでは？
our... victory?
We've been saved!
（部下）助かったのか
（部下）ウオーッ！
確かに 我らの勝利は決定的だ
It's true that our victory has been assured.
…が しかし
But...
崖の上に現れた援軍
あれは 一体 どこから来たのだ？
Just where did those reinforcements on top of the cliffs come from?
5,000～6,000は いる
There's five or six thousand.
A force like that can't be organized offhand.
あれだけの軍を
にわかに編成することはできぬ
あらかじめ準備されていたのは
明らかだが…
It's clear that they were prepared beforehand.
（壁）王翦将軍は
私では姜燕に勝てないことを―
Does this mean that General Wang Jian thought I could not win against Jiang Yan from the beginning?
初めから見越していた
…ということか？
敗軍の将には死を
それが戦場の鉄則だ 姜燕
The general of the losing army is given death!
That is an ironclad rule of the battlefield, Jiang Yan.
（部下）姜燕さま
ここは我らが食い止めます！
Lord Jiang Yan, we will stop them here!
You alone must escape!
（部下）お１人だけでも脱出を！
だが 私は慈悲深い
But I am a merciful man.
助かる道を
ひとつだけ うぬに与える
I will give you one means of escape.
これより この私に仕えるのだ
From this point onward, work for me.
私を主(あるじ)とあがめ 忠誠を誓うならば
If you swear loyalty to me and respect me as your master,
うぬの配下も含めて
全員 命を助けてやろう
I will spare your life as well as the lives of your subordinates.
What?!
（部下）なんだと？
何だ？ 投降を勧めているのか？
What? He's recommending they surrender?
You won't be mere underlings.
（王翦）下僕にするのではない
うぬら全員に土地を与え
十分な待遇を約束する
I will give you all land and I promise you ample recognition.
そして 姜燕
うぬには 私の側近となってもらう
And Jiang Yan... you will become my aide.
（姜燕の部下）
こんなときに人材登用？
He's appointing people at a time like this?!
He says he'll give us land and the ranks of top military commanders?!
（部下）一武将のぶんざいで
我らに土地を与えるだと？
Do you think we'll be taken in by such nonsense?!
（部下）そんなざれ言に
ダマされると思うのか！
What's more, the war still isn't over! Do not mock us!
そもそも戦は まだ終わっておらぬ
我らを愚弄するな！
I am speaking in earnest.
私は本気で言っている
私の国は うぬのような
戦の強い男を必要としているのだ
My country will require men
that are powerful in battle like you.
国？
Country?
What is General Wang Jian saying?
何を言っているのだ？ 王翦将軍は
悪いようにはせぬ 姜燕
You will not regret it, Jiang Yan.
But if you refuse...
だが 断るならば…
これより この囲地が
血の海と化すことになるぞ
this enclosed land will become a sea of blood.
（部下）ほう…
He penetrated our shields made with specially-tempered iron. Impressive.
特別に鍛え上げた鉄で作らせた盾を
貫くとは… さすが
（部下）
王翦さまに弓を引いたとあらば…
He drew his bow on Lord Wang Jian...
（部下）八つ裂き
…ということで よろしいですか？
Do we have permission to tear him limb from limb?
ならん　生け捕りだ
No. Take him alive.
Wang Jian. There is one thing I would like to ask.
（姜燕）王翦…
ひとつだけ聞きたいことがある
（部下）姜燕！
それ以上 近づくな！ 弓を捨てろ！
Jiang Yan! Do not get any closer! Drop your bow!
戦の序盤で こちらが
優勢になったのは 貴様の策略か？
Was it your plan for me to be superior in the opening of this battle?
そのとおりだ
Exactly.
What do you mean, Lord Jiang Yan?!
（部下）
どういうことですか？ 姜燕さま
我らが あの崖の上の秦国軍の
出現に気づかなかったのには―
There is a reason I did not notice the presence of that State of Qin Army up on the cliffs.
理由がある
（姜燕）
あれは よそから来たのではなく
They didn't come here from somewhere far away.
They were lying hidden nearby before the battle started.
ここで戦が始まる前から
潜ませてあったのだ
（部下）戦が始まる前から？
Before the battle started?!
ここが戦場になると読んでいた
…ということですか？
Are you saying they predicted that this place would become a battlefield?
王翦将軍は 私に5,000の兵を与えて
姜燕を討てと命じたとき
When General Wang Jian gave me 5,000 soldiers and ordered me to slay Jiang Yan...
did he already have his army hidden?
既に
この地に軍を潜ませていたのか
私は囮にすぎなかったのだ
I was nothing but a decoy!
だが…
But...
（姜燕の部下）
しかし 軍を潜ませようにも―
But even if you had your army hidden, there is no way you could have formed an army like that and kept it secret from us!
我らの目を盗んで そのような軍を
作れるわけがありません
（部下）分散した秦国軍に
合わせて 我らも分散し
We knew the distribution of the State of Qin Army as well as our own as well as all of their movements.
ヤツらの動きは
全て把握していました
If an army of 5,000 had disappeared, we should certainly have noticed!
5,000人もの軍が消えれば
必ず気づいたはずです
No, we were not aware of everything.
いや
全てを把握していたわけではない
There was just one army we did not have a thorough grasp of.
１つだけ
つかみきれていない軍があった
（姜燕）それは ヤツの本軍だ
That was his headquarters.
早々に
後退を始めた王翦の本軍だけは―
Having started to retreat so quickly, we did not know the details regarding Wang Jian's headquarters' scale or equipment.
規模や装備など
詳しいことが分かっていなかった
It is true that while we were pursuing the movements of the retreating enemy headquarters,
確かに 後退する敵の本軍の
動きは追っていたが
we didn't know what their numbers were...
その数までは…
（部下）我らが知らぬ間に
本軍を分割していたのか
So the headquarters split apart without us knowing?
So then what appeared on top of the cliffs
ということは 崖の上に現れたのは
分割された王翦将軍の本軍
was the other part of General Wang Jian's headquarters?
（姜燕）王翦は ここに囲地という
特殊な地形があることに気づき
Wang Jian realized that this enclosed land allowed itself to special military tactics
ここが戦場になると読んだ
and predicted it would become a battlefield.
いや 正確に言えば
囮を使うことによって―
Or, no, to be more precise,
by using a decoy, he induced this place to be chosen as the battlefield.
我らが ここを戦場に選ぶように
しむけることができると読んだ
読みどおりに ここを
戦場に選んだ我らを討つためには
And so he could defeat us, having chosen this place as the battlefield as he predicted,
あらかじめ
ここに軍を潜ませておく必要があり
it was necessary for him to hide an army here beforehand.
（姜燕）その軍を編成するためには
In order to organize that army, he needed to retreat his headquarters quickly.
早々に
本軍を後退させる必要があった
その後退を
自然なものと見せかけるために―
And in order to make that retreat seem natural,
Wang Jian had to make it seem as though his army
王翦は戦の序盤から 我らに押され
was fighting a hard battle and being pushed back from the outset of the war.
苦戦を強いられているように
見せかけたのだ
（部下）なんと！
（部下）そんなところから…
What...?!
He planned it that far in advance?!
（壁）一体 何なのだ？ この戦は
Just what the hell is this battle?!
何手先まで読めば こうなる？
Just how many moves did he predict to reach this outcome?!
It is hard to believe.
信じ難いことだ
相手の心理と戦局の推移
With only a few clues, to predict this far regarding the opponent's psychology and the changes of the state of battle...
僅かな手がかりを基に
ここまで読み切るとは…
It is beyond the realm of humans.
（姜燕）
もはや人間の域を超えている
（姜燕）やはり 怪物だな
Truly a monster.
あのお方は
Is what that man is.
（廉頗）ア～ハハハッ…
ア～ハハハッ…
やはり わしの読みどおりに
動いたのぅ 王翦
You did just what I predicted, Wang Jian!
（ﾅﾚｰﾀｰ）
そのとき 不思議な現象が起こった
At that moment, a strange phenomenon took place.
That battlefield that had been filled with angry roars suddenly went silent.
怒号で埋め尽くされていた戦場から
音が消えたのである
秦国 魏国 関係なく―
Those of the State of Qin and of the State of Wei,
この場にいる全兵士が動きを止め
それを凝視した
all soldiers in this area stopped moving and stared.
And they all uniformly felt their body temperatures rise.
そして 皆が一様に
体温が上昇するのを感じた
Th... This is Lian Po!
こ… これが 廉頗
（信(しん)）うん？
What... is this feeling...?
（信）何だ？ この感じ
This feeling...
（信）この感じは―
王騎(おうき)将軍が 戦場に
打って出たときと そっくりだ
It's just like when General Wang Qi would enter a battlefield.
So you've finally started moving, have you, my lord?
（輪虎(りんこ)）
ついに動かれたようですね 殿
フッ… 間違いねえ
There's no doubt about it...
（信）天下の…
That guy is... the greatest general under the heavens!
大将軍だ！
Preview
The Caliber
of a General
End